Welcome, brothers and sisters.
兄弟姉妹 ようこそ
In this month’s program,
今月のプログラムでは
we’ll review who the May 2020 Watchtower
「ものみの塔」2020年
5月号で説明された
identified as “the king of the north,”
「北の王」について考えます
and we’ll learn how knowing this
この預言は私たちにどんな
影響を与えるでしょうか
affects each one of us.
諦めずに頑張り続けることが
We’ll also see
how perseverance helps us
エホバにいっそう仕え続ける上で
どのように役立つかも考えます
reach our spiritual goals.
And we’ll debut an exciting new series
また特に10代の皆さん
のために用意された
made especially for teenagers.
新しいシリーズの第1回を
ご覧いただきます
This is JW Broadcasting for May 2021.
2021年5月の
JW Broadcasting®です
My theme is “‘The King of the North’
in the Time of the End.”
この話のテーマは
「終わりの時の『北の王』」です
In recent years, the Russian government
最近 ロシア政府は国内の
兄弟姉妹を迫害しています
has persecuted our brothers and sisters
who live in that country.
ご存じのように 警察は王国会館に
踏み込み 集会を中止させています
You’ve heard reports
about the police invading Kingdom Halls
and breaking up meetings.
政府はエホバの証人に
The government has labeled
Jehovah’s Witnesses
「過激主義グループ」という
レッテルを貼っています
as an “extremist group.”
It has seized our properties
and imprisoned our brothers.
私たちの不動産を没収し
兄弟たちを投獄しています
Please watch a brief video
ロシアの兄弟姉妹がどんな試練に
遭っているのかをまとめた
that reviews some of the trials
Jehovah’s people in Russia have faced.
短いビデオをご覧ください
2017年4月20日
ロシア連邦最高裁判所は
On April 20, 2017,
the Supreme Court
of the Russian Federation criminalized
エホバの証人の活動が
違法であるとの判決を下しました
the activity of Jehovah’s Witnesses.
2019年7月4日の時点で 当局は
As of July 4, 2019,
authorities have progressively
seized 131 of the properties
エホバの証人が所有する
131の不動産を次々と差し押さえ
owned by Jehovah’s Witnesses,
さらに60の不動産を
差し押さえる予定です
with an additional 60 properties
subject to confiscation.
One of the seized properties
ソルネチノエにある元ロシア支部の
施設も差し押さえられました
was the former
Russia branch complex in Solnechnoye.
このビデオの制作中も 当局は
At the time of filming,
the Russian authorities continue
エホバの証人への
激しい攻撃を続けています
their aggressive attack
on Jehovah’s Witnesses.
As of August 17, 2020,
2020年8月17日の時点で
there were 42 Witnesses
who were in pretrial detention
42人が公判前勾留されたり
投獄されたりしています
or sentenced to prison,
32 who were under house arrest,
32人が自宅で拘禁されており
and 169 who were not allowed
to leave their hometown.
169人は自分が住む町から
出ることが許されていません
All have been charged with organizing,
その全員に 「過激主義」組織の
活動を組織し
participating in, or financing the activity
それに参加し または資金を提供した
容疑が掛けられています
of a so-called “extremist” organization.
At least 380 Witnesses were,
at the time, under investigation
その時点で 19歳から89歳までの
—ranging in age from 19 to 89 years old.
少なくとも380人のエホバの証人が
取り調べを受けています
What has this meant
for the individuals affected?
では 具体的にどんなことが
起きているのでしょうか
As an example,
例えば 2018年6月3日
on June 3, 2018,
セルゲイ・クリモフ兄弟が
逮捕されました
Brother Sergey Klimov was arrested.
Local authorities initiated
兄弟は刑事責任を問われ
2カ月間公判前勾留されました
criminal charges against him,
placing him
in pretrial detention for two months.
その後 勾留期間が
7回も延長されたので
This detention was extended seven times,
兄弟は最終的に裁判に掛けられ
判決が下されるまでに
separating him from his wife and family
for a year and five months,
before he was finally tried and sentenced.
妻や家族から1年5カ月も
引き離されました
On November 5, 2019,
2019年11月5日に
6年の懲役刑を言い渡されました
he was sentenced to six years in prison.
Two of our dear young people in Russia,
若いエゴール・バラノフ兄弟と
ダリア・ドゥロワ姉妹は
Brother Yegor Baranov
and Sister Darya Dulova,
有罪判決を受けて長期の拘禁刑を
言い渡される可能性があります
are courageously facing criminal conviction
and potential long-term imprisonment.
バラノフ兄弟はまだ19歳です
Brother Baranov is only 19 years old.
ドゥロワ姉妹は家宅捜索を
受けた時 まだ18歳でした
When the authorities raided her home,
Sister Dulova was only 18 years old.
jw.orgのニュースルームでは
最新情報を得られます
By means of the Newsroom on jw.org,
we are informed of updated news events.
This page includes links to name lists
信仰ゆえに投獄されている
of Witnesses
currently imprisoned for their faith,
エホバの証人のリストにも
アクセスできます
which can help us include
them specifically in our prayers.
名前を挙げて祈ることができるでしょう
ロシアの兄弟姉妹は
どんな反対に遭っても
Our brothers and sisters in Russia
are resolved to remain loyal to Jehovah
エホバに忠実を保つ決意をしています
despite any opposition,
そして エホバがいつもそばにいて
くださることを確信しています
and they put their confidence
in him in the assurance
that Jehovah is on their side!
It shouldn’t surprise us
この強力な政府が
that this powerful government
has been persecuting
法律を守る穏やかな兄弟姉妹を
迫害しているとしても
our peaceful,
law-abiding brothers and sisters.
意外なことではありません
なぜですか
Why not?
Because that government
is fulfilling Bible prophecy!
聖書に そのようなことが起きると
予告されていたからです
Please find Daniel chapter 11.
ダニエル 11章を見てみましょう
In verse 40, it refers
to what the Bible calls
40節では 「北の王」と呼ばれる王
のことが述べられています
“the king of the north.”
その王について
11:41にはこうあります
Of that “king,” Daniel 11:41 says:
“He will also enter
into the land of the Decoration,
「［北の王は］『美しい地』にも入り
多くの国が倒れることになります」
and many lands will be made to stumble.”
Today, Russia and its allies
今 北の王となっているのは
ロシアとそれを支持する国々です
are filling the role
of the king of the north.
Daniel foretold that this king would enter
ダニエルによると その王は
「美しい地」に入ります
“the land of the Decoration,”
meaning that he would interfere
in a significant way
これは 神の民の活動を
妨げようとする という意味です
with the activities of God’s people.
「ものみの塔」2020年5月号に
あった通り
As discussed in the May 2020 Watchtower,
ロシアとそれを支持する国々は
Russia and its allies
are not the first political power
北の王として行動した
最初の強国ではありません
to act as the king of the north,
but they may well be the last.
むしろ 最後の強国になるでしょう
In this program, we will do three things:
この話では 3つの点を取り上げます
First,
1つ目に ダニエル 11章の預言が
どのように実現してきたか
we’ll briefly trace
the fulfillment of the prophecy
recorded in Daniel chapter 11.
手短に振り返ります
2つ目に この預言が今どのように
実現しているかに注目します
Second, we’ll look at how that prophecy
is being fulfilled today.
3つ目に この預言が私たちの生き方に
どんな影響を与えるかを考えます
And third, we’ll discuss
how knowing this information
should affect the decisions that we make.
Brother Herman van Selm,
a helper to the Writing Committee,
執筆委員会の援助者
ヘルマナス･ファン･セルム兄弟と一緒に
will help us review
some of the key points of the prophecy
ダニエル 11章の預言の主な点を
振り返りたいと思います
recorded in Daniel chapter 11.
Thank you, Herman,
for helping me with this presentation.
ファン･セルム兄弟
よろしくお願いします
It’s a pleasure to be with you, Ken.
こちらこそ よろしくお願いします
Thank you for inviting me.
お招きありがとうございます
First, let’s briefly trace
まず この預言がこれまでどのように
実現してきたかを振り返りましょう
how the prophecy has been fulfilled so far.
The prophecy in Daniel chapter 11 mentions
ダニエル 11章の預言には
「北の王」と「南の王」が出てきます
“the king of the north”
and “the king of the south.”
Now, why are they described like that?
なぜそう呼ばれているのでしょうか
Well, initially,
当初 この2つの強国は
these powers were located north and south
イスラエルの文字通り
北と南に位置していました
of the literal land of Israel,
それで 北の王と南の王と
呼ばれています
thus the names king of the north
and king of the south.
2つの強国は 2つの王座に
例えられます
These powers could be viewed as two thrones.
Over time, those thrones have been occupied
この2つの王座には
さまざまな強国が座ります
by various political powers
そして 北の王と南の王は
覇権争いをします
and these rival kings compete
for world domination.
And what about Jehovah’s people?
エホバの民はどうなりますか
They are right at the center
of this conflict.
北の王と南の王の影響を直接受けます
But let’s start at the beginning.
では 時代順に考えましょう
Ken,
クック兄弟
what is the origin
of the kings of the north and of the south?
最初の北の王と南の王は誰でしたか
The kings of the north and of the south
北の王も 南の王も
アレクサンドロス大王が
設立した帝国から興りました
both rose from the empire
established by Alexander the Great.
1つの王朝はイスラエルの南に
位置するエジプトを治めました
One line of kings ruled over Egypt,
which is south of Israel.
And that dynasty was the first
この王朝が最初の南の王になりました
to fill the role of king of the south.
During this period, another line of kings
そのころ 別の王朝がイスラエルの
北の方にある地域を治め
ruled an area north of Israel
and those kings filled the role
北の王になりました
of king of the north.
Then the Roman Empire took over
その後 ローマ帝国が
北の王になりました
as king of the north.
As discussed in the May 2020 Watchtower,
「ものみの塔」2020年5月号に
述べられていた通り
God’s people are the focal point
ダニエル 11章の預言が特に
注意を向けているのは 神の民です
of the prophecy
recorded in Daniel chapter 11.
ダニエルに話した天使は
その預言が与えられたのは
The angel who spoke with Daniel
said that the prophecy
would help him
“understand what will befall your people”
「あなたの民に起きる事柄をあなたに
理解させるため」だと言いました
—that is, the nation of Israel.
つまり イスラエル国民に
起きる事柄です
では どんなことが起きましたか
And what, in fact, happened?
Well, the Jewish nation
was God’s people until 33 C.E.
イスラエル国民は
西暦33年まで神の民でした
But after that, a change occurred.
でもその後 変化が生じます
Jehovah poured out his holy spirit
エホバはキリストの弟子たちに
聖なる力を注ぎました
on Christ’s followers.
And from then on,
その時以降 真のクリスチャン会衆が
神の民になりました
the congregation of true Christians
became God’s people.
Galatians 6:16 refers to them
ガラテア 6:16では
その会衆のことが「神のイスラエル」
と呼ばれています
as “the Israel of God.”
That point is significant
この点は重要です
because the kings of the north and south
can only be identified
ある国や政府を
北の王や南の王と呼べるのは
when there is a clearly defined group
of God’s people on earth.
神の民が地上でグループとして
はっきり見分けられるときだけです
Why is that the case?
なぜそう言えますか
Because, as we just considered,
先ほど考えた通り
the angel had told Daniel
天使はこの預言が 神の民に起きる事柄
に関するものだと述べたからです
that the prophecy centers on God’s people.
In the second century C.E.,
西暦2世紀 真のクリスチャンは
true Christians were overgrown
雑草のような偽のクリスチャンに
覆い隠されてしまいました
by weedlike false Christians.
In his illustration
of the wheat and the weeds,
小麦と雑草の例えで
イエスはそのことを予告していました
Jesus foretold that this would happen.
That illustration is recorded
この例えは マタイ 13:36-43
に書かれています
at Matthew 13:36-43.
So from the second century onward,
それで 2世紀以降
we can no longer identify
an organized group of true Christians.
真のクリスチャンの組織されたグループ
を見分けることはできなくなりました
And, as we considered, for that same reason,
ですから 先ほど述べられた通り
we also cannot identify
北の王と南の王も存在しなかった
ということになります
the king of the north
and the king of the south.
But in the 1870’s, a group of Bible students
しかし 1870年代
聖書研究者たちのグループが
偽のクリスチャンから分かれ始めました
began to separate itself
from false Christians.
This group,
チャールズ･T･ラッセルを含む
このグループは
which included Charles T. Russell,
rejected teachings
聖書に基づいていない教えを退けました
that were not based on the Bible.
And like the first-century Christians,
1世紀のクリスチャンと同様
神の言葉の真理を人々に教えたのです
they promoted the truths
taught in God’s Word.
Now this group underwent a development
マラキ 3:1には
that is foretold at Malachi 3:1.
このグループが行うことが
あらかじめ予告されていました
They were the “messenger”
彼らは「使者」として エホバの前に
「道を整える」ことになっていたのです
who would “clear up a way” before Jehovah.
And as events that followed prove,
その後の進展からはっきり分かる通り
this group clearly had God’s backing.
このグループは神に導かれていました
So from the 1870’s onward,
それで1870年代以降
when true Christians began
to organize themselves as a group,
真のクリスチャンがグループとして
組織されるようになりました
we can again identify the political powers
それに伴って どの強国が
that fill the roles of the king of the north
北の王と南の王なのかが
分かるようになりました
and king of the south.
At that time in history,
歴史のその時点で
英国は最大の強国でした
Britain was the dominant political force
ですから この国が南の王でした
and it filled the role
of the king of the south.
Amazingly, it was also in the 1870’s
驚いたことに 同じ1870年代
ドイツ帝国が台頭し
that the German Empire emerged
and soon began to challenge Britain
間もなくイギリスと覇権争いを
するようになりました
for world domination.
This political power now filled the role
この強国ドイツが北の王になったのです
of the king of the north.
Daniel 11:25, 26 indicate
ダニエル 11:25, 26によると
that the two kings would clash
この2人の王は衝突し
北の王は戦いで多くの兵士を失います
and that the king of the north
would lose many soldiers in the battle.
And that is exactly what happened
このことは 第1次世界大戦中
に生じました
during World War I.
And it was during that war
英国は アメリカ合衆国と同盟を結び
密接に協力するようになりました
that Britain and its close ally,
the United States,
forged a special bond.
終わりの時代のこの時から
手を組んだ英国と米国
So from this point on,
during these last days,
the Anglo-American power
つまり英米同盟が南の王になりました
has been the king of the south.
That brings us to our second point:
では2つ目の点を考えましょう
How has Daniel chapter 11 been fulfilled
ダニエル 11章の預言は
その時から今に至るまで
どのように実現してきましたか
from that time onward
until recent times?
During World War I,
第1次世界大戦中
the king of the north
and the king of the south
北の王も南の王も 戦争で戦うことを
拒んだ神の民を迫害しました
persecuted those of God’s people
who refused to fight in the war.
The king of the south even threw into jail
南の王は 率先して伝道を行って
いた人たちを刑務所に入れました
those who were taking the lead
in the preaching work.
ではこれから 北の王について
詳しく考えてみましょう
But let’s take a closer look
at the king of the north.
Has the political power filling that role
終わりの時代に北の王に
なったのはどの国ですか
changed during the last days?
入れ替わりがありましたか
神の民をどう扱ってきたでしょうか
And how has it treated God’s people?
The identity of the king of the north
終わりの時代に北の王に
なったのは 3つの強国です
has changed three times during the last days.
Starting in the 1870’s
through to the end of the second world war,
1870年代から
第2次世界大戦の終わりまで
the German Empire
ドイツ帝国が北の王として行動しました
filled the role of the king of the north.
In the period leading up to
and including World War II,
その間 特に第2次世界大戦中
北の王は神の民を容赦なく迫害しました
it persecuted God’s people without mercy,
imprisoning thousands of our brothers
大勢の兄弟たちが投獄され
約1500人が亡くなりました
and killing hundreds of them.
Who replaced the German Empire
as the king of the north?
ドイツ帝国の後
北の王になったのは誰ですか
That’s an important question, Herman.
それは大切な質問です
After World War II,
第2次世界大戦後 ソビエト連邦が
北の王になりました
the Soviet Union took on that role.
It also attacked God’s people,
そして神の民を攻撃し 投獄したり
シベリアに追放したりしました
imprisoning them or sending them into exile.
でも ダニエル 11:34によると
But, Ken, Daniel 11:34 says
that they—that is, God’s people—
「彼ら」つまり神の民は
「多少の助けを得ます」
would be “given a little help.”
What’s the significance of that statement?
これにはどんな意味がありますか
This passage points forward to the time
この言葉は ソビエト連邦が崩壊した時
のことについて述べています
when the Soviet Union collapsed.
Although God’s people suffered terribly
under that government,
神の民はその政権の下で
つらい目に遭いましたが
they were “given a little help.”
「多少の助けを得ま［した］」
In what way?
どのようにですか
After the USSR collapsed,
ソビエト連邦が崩壊した後 神の民は
何年も自由に崇拝を行えました
God’s people there could worship freely
for a number of years.
In time, though, Russia and its allies
しかしやがて ロシアとそれを支持する
国々が北の王になりました
took on the role of the king of the north.
And like the other powers
that filled the role of king of the north,
ロシアとそれを支持する国々は
それまでの北の王と同様
神の民を抑圧し続けてきました
this government has continued to oppress
God’s people.
Let’s watch the following video
次のビデオで この預言がどのように
実現してきたかを見てみましょう
that outlines what has happened.
Daniel received a prophecy
ダニエルは2人の王が
敵対することを預言しました
about the coming of two rivals:
“the king of the north”
「北の王」と「南の王」です
and “the king of the south.”
How has it been fulfilled?
どのように実現してきましたか
1800年代後半 ドイツ帝国が
北の王になりました
In the late 1800’s, the German Empire
became the king of the north.
That government brought
ドイツ政府は 「力と勇気を奮い起こし
大きな軍隊で南の王を攻め」ました
its “power and . . . heart
“against the king of the south
with a large army.”
世界で2番目の規模の
海軍を持っていました
In fact, its navy was
the second largest on earth.
では 誰が南の王になりましたか
Who became the king of the south?
The alliance between Britain
軍事同盟を結んだ英国と米国です
and the United States.
He fought during World War I
第1次世界大戦中 「非常に
強大な軍隊で」戦いました
“with an exceedingly large
and mighty army.”
He “swept away” and “humbled”
そして 北の王を「押し流［し］」
「打ち負か［し］」ました
the king of the north.
But that was not the end
でも 北の王は活動を
やめたわけではありません
of the king of the north.
He turned his attention to and then hurled
「聖なる契約に」注意を向け
「糾弾」を浴びせます
“denunciations against the holy covenant.”
そして 「日ごとの犠牲」
を除き去ります
He removed “the constant feature”
by limiting the freedom of God’s people
神の民が伝道を行う自由を制限し
to preach,
天に行くよう選ばれたクリスチャンと
その仲間たちを大勢投獄し
imprisoning many,
and even killing hundreds
of God’s anointed ones
殺すことさえしたのです
and their fellow workers.
After Germany was defeated in World War II,
ドイツが第2次世界大戦で敗れた後
the Soviet Union
ソビエト連邦が北の王になりました
became the king of the north.
It worked with the king of the south
北の王は南の王と手を組み
to “put in place the disgusting thing
「荒廃をもたらす極めて
不快なものを据え」ました
that causes desolation”
—the United Nations.
国際連合です
1900年代の初めから
Beginning in the early 1900’s,
ソビエト政府は連邦内の
宗教を排除しようとしました
the Soviet government tried to eliminate
religion in the lands under its control,
こうして 「自分の父祖たちの神を
無視」するという預言が実現しました
fulfilling the words
that he would “show no regard
for the God of his fathers.”
天の神ではなく
「要塞の神」をたたえたのです
He gave glory, not to the God of heaven,
but “to the god of fortresses.”
預言通り 北の王は南の王に軍事力
を行使し 「彼と押し合い」ました
As prophesied,
he used this military might
against the king of the south
by engaging “with him in a pushing.”
英米同盟とソビエト連邦は
覇権争いを続け
Anglo-America competed
with the Soviet Union
for world domination,
世界中の戦争や紛争に関わりました
fighting in and supporting wars
and political struggles around the globe.
1991年にソビエト連邦が崩壊した後
After the Soviet Union collapsed in 1991,
it was unclear who would fill the role
of the king of the north.
誰が北の王になるのか
はっきり分かりませんでした
For a time, God’s people there
しばらくの間 神の民は
伝道や崇拝を自由に行えました
had been able to preach
and worship peacefully.
しかし近年 ロシアとそれを支持する
国々は 南の王を押し返しています
But in recent years, Russia and its allies
have pushed back at the king of the south.
Both kings have accused each other
どちらの王も相手のサイバー攻撃
を非難しています
of destructive cyber and economic attacks.
北の王が攻撃しているのは
南の王だけではありません
But the king of the north has not limited
his attacks to the king of the south.
As foretold, he also entered
預言通り クリスチャンの
活動領域である
“into the land of the Decoration”
「『美しい地』にも入［って］」います
—our realm of spiritual activity.
ロシア当局は今も真の崇拝への
攻撃を続けています
Today, Russian authorities continue
to attack true worship.
私たちはそのような迫害を
予期していました
We expect such persecution,
そしてそれが終わることも知っています
but we also expect it to end.
私たちの王イエス･キリストは
どんな人間の政府よりも強力な方です
Our King, Jesus Christ,
is more powerful than any human government.
イエスは間もなく
北の王と南の王だけでなく
Soon he will destroy
not only the kings of the north and the south
全ての敵を滅ぼします
but all of his enemies,
そして 神を愛する人たちを
救出するのです
and he will deliver God’s loyal people.
That was a powerful and touching video!
本当に信仰が強まる
感動的なビデオでした
How are our brothers and sisters coping
with the current persecution?
兄弟姉妹は今 どのように
迫害に立ち向かっていますか
Let’s take a look.
ビデオをご覧ください
And what you’re going to see
will break your heart
兄弟姉妹の様子を見て
心が痛むかもしれません
but also strengthen your faith.
でも信仰が強まるでしょう
At 6:00 a.m.,
朝6時 ドアを激しくたたく音で
目が覚めました
my husband and I were woken up
by a loud bang on the door.
夫がドアを開けると
As soon as my husband had opened the door,
人がなだれ込んできて
「床に伏せろ」と言いました
people burst in shouting,
“Everyone on the floor!”
その人たちは夫をキッチンに連れていき
何かをするように厳しく命じていました
I saw them taking my husband into the kitchen
and heard them
very aggressively
ordering him to do something.
大きな音がしたので 暴力を
受けていることが分かりました
Then I heard some noise, and I realized
that he was being beaten.
My husband, Feliks, and I
フェリクスと私は
ショッピングモールから
駐車場に向かって歩いていました
were on our way back from the shopping mall
to the car park.
黒い窓ガラスの車が目の前に止まり
A jeep with tinted windows
blocked our path, and people
武装した人たちが降りてきて
「地面に伏せろ 動くな」と言いました
with weapons
jumped out, shouting:
“On the ground!
Don’t move!”
2人とも車に押し付けられました
We were thrown against the vehicle.
フェリクスは拘置所に送られ
そこに1年いました
Feliks was sent
to a pretrial detention facility,
where he spent a year.
ドアの音がした時から祈り始めました
From the very first bang on the door,
I began praying to Jehovah
for wisdom, calmness,
「知恵と穏やかな心を下さい
正しく決定し 行動できるよう
聖なる力を与えてください」
and for holy spirit
so that I could make the right decisions
and act in the right way.
一日中祈りました
And for the whole day, I was praying.
エホバは全ての祈りに答えてくれました
Jehovah answered all my prayers,
and I felt that he was close at my side.
すぐそばにいてくださいました
裁判所の審問の前はいつも
怖くて気持ちが落ち着きませんでした
Before each court hearing
when I was very afraid
and felt overwhelmed by emotion
and couldn’t calm myself down,
it was prayer
でも祈ると 穏やかな
気持ちになれました
that helped me to settle down.
When they took us for interrogation,
取調室に連れていかれる時に
とても不安になりました
I started panicking and, at that moment,
それで 「何か前向きになれることを
考えなきゃ」と思いました
I realized that I needed
to meditate on something positive.
So I thought,
「そうだ 賛美の歌を歌おう」
と思いました
‘I need to sing our songs.’
And just one song came into my mind:
「神はあなたを強い人にしてくださる」
の歌が思い浮かびました
“He Will Make You Strong.”
勇気が湧いてきました
It really strengthened me.
自分の子さえも与えたエホバは
Those words
about how Jehovah gave his Son for us
どんな時も私たちを愛し
守ってくださいます
show he loves us and will never leave us.
Brothers and sisters
兄弟姉妹が祈ってくれています
pray and tell me
私のためにも祈っている
と言ってくれました
that they are praying for me.
It gives me the feeling that I am part
家族に支えてもらっているように
感じました
of a large family.
After the interrogation,
取り調べの後 夫は家に帰されました
he was sent home.
My husband and I
私たちはクリスチャンの日課を
しっかり守っています
continue to stick to our spiritual routine.
家族の崇拝を欠かさず行い
伝道も一生懸命頑張っています
We continue to conduct family worship,
and we are always in the ministry.
兄弟姉妹はずっと支えてくれています
Our brothers and sisters
constantly support us.
優しい言葉を書いて
元気づけてくれます
They write kind words;
they commend us;
励みになる聖句も書いてくれます
they send us
encouraging scriptures from the Bible.
In September 2019, Feliks was found guilty
2019年9月 フェリクスは
一般矯正施設での
3年の刑を言い渡されました
and sentenced to three years
in a general regime colony.
When he and the other brothers arrived there,
フェリクスたちは施設に着くと
係官たちに殴打されました
they were beaten up by officers
from the colony.
Feliks told me
フェリクスは殴打されている間
エホバに祈りました
that he prayed
while he was being beaten,
and he noticed that at that moment,
he stopped feeling the pain.
そうしたら 痛みを
感じなくなったそうです
While he is behind bars,
フェリクスは拘禁されている間も
手紙で家族の崇拝をしてくれました
Feliks tries to conduct
family worship with me by letters.
He picks certain themes
and some specific questions.
テーマや質問を考えてくれました
Then I do research
私は出版物を調べて返事を書きました
in the publications
and send back what I find.
The scripture at Isaiah chapter 30
really strengthens me,
イザヤ30章の聖句に
とても力づけられました
where it says that “your strength will be
「平静を保ち
信頼するなら 力を得る」
in keeping calm and showing trust.”
Although I tend to worry,
私は心配性ですが
エホバを全く信頼していれば
穏やかな気持ちでいられます
I understand that calmness is expressed
by fully trusting in Jehovah.
I have become stronger
because thanks to Jehovah,
エホバのおかげで強くなれました
in a way, I have developed almost a shell
以前ならおびえていたようなことでも
怖くなくなりました
against the difficulties
エホバへの信頼と信仰が
支えになっています
that used to scare me.
That confidence and faith help me.
Jehovah was with me,
エホバは共にいてくださいました
and he will remain
これからもそばにいてくださいます
close by me,
and we will be made stronger thanks to him,
エホバの支えがあれば
試練を乗り越える力が得られます
and we will get through these trials.
How can we develop courage
私たちはどうすればロシアの兄弟姉妹
のような勇気を持てるでしょうか
like our brothers and sisters in Russia?
Well, we must be convinced
そのためには 聖書の預言は
必ず実現する ということを
that the prophecies in the Bible
are trustworthy.
確信していなければなりません
That was a topic discussed
この点を 統治体の
デービッド･スプレーン兄弟が
by Brother David Splane of the Governing Body
in the following Morning Worship program.
朝の崇拝で取り上げてくださいました
Now, if you’d just
今日の聖句をご覧ください
take a look at today’s text,
it says: “Come and witness
「来て エホバが行うことを見よ」
とあります
the activities of Jehovah”—witness.
証人になるように ということです
ある辞書によると 証人とは
Now, according to a dictionary,
a witness is someone
who has personal knowledge of something.
ある事柄について個人的な知識を
持っている人のことです
So how can we be Witnesses of Jehovah?
では どうすればエホバの証人に
なれるでしょうか
What personal knowledge
エホバの行いについて どんな
個人的な知識を持っていますか
do we have of his activities?
Well, first of all,
we can testify to the fact
1つ目に エホバが将来を見通すことが
できる ということを知っています
that Jehovah can see into the future.
And when he does that,
he is right 100 percent of the time.
エホバが見通しを誤る
ことなどありません
And second, we know that no one can prevent
2つ目に エホバが予告したことを
妨げることは誰にもできません
what Jehovah foresees from coming true.
All of Jehovah’s prophecies come true.
エホバの預言は全て実現します
Now, to illustrate the first point,
ではまず エホバが将来を
見通すことができることを示す
that Jehovah can see into the future,
let’s consider two remarkable prophecies
2つの際立った預言に注目しましょう
concerning the destruction
of Jerusalem and its temple.
エルサレムと神殿が破壊される
ことについての預言です
Now, we know that
through the prophet Jeremiah,
エホバは預言者エレミヤを通して
エルサレムと神殿が
Jehovah foretold
that Jerusalem and the temple
バビロニア人によって破壊
されることを予告しました
would be destroyed by the Babylonians.
Did it come true?
どうなりましたか
予告通りになりました
Absolutely—in 607 B.C.E.
紀元前607年です
But Jehovah went further.
エホバはその先も見通していました
He said that Jerusalem would be rebuilt.
エルサレムの再建です
“They will rebuild the ancient ruins;
こうあります 「彼らは
古い廃虚を建て直す
“they will raise up
the desolated places of the past,
過去に荒れ果てた場所を復興し
and they will restore the devastated cities.”
破壊された町々を元通りにする」
And true worship would also be restored.
真の崇拝も回復します
So that was quite a level of knowledge.
かなり詳しい情報です
But there’s more.
でもこれだけではありません
Jehovah went further.
エホバは 人々がいつまでも真の崇拝を
Jehovah also indicated
that the spiritual revival wouldn’t last.
続けるわけではないことを
明らかにしました
Now, that is remarkable.
注目すべき点です
And it’s implied by what we read
in the second part
ダニエル 9:26の後半を読むと
of Daniel 9:26.
そのことが分かります
I’d like you to have a look at this.
どうぞご覧ください
We’re going to be reading
非常に興味深い2つの
ポイントに注目します
two parts of this verse,
and it’s quite interesting
ダニエル 9:26です
—Daniel 9:26.
So now, what’s our objective here?
この聖句から理解できる点があります
It’s to see that Jerusalem and its temple
それは エルサレムと神殿が
もう一度破壊され
would be destroyed a second time
人々が真の崇拝を行わなくなる
ということです
and that true worship would not last.
It says in the second part of verse 26:
26節の後半です
“And the people of a leader who is coming
「やがて来る指導者に率いられた人々が
will destroy the city and the holy place.”
都市と聖なる場所を滅ぼ［す］」
Now, when these words were written,
この言葉が書かれた当時
Jerusalem and the temple
were already in ruins.
エルサレムと神殿は
まだ荒れ果てていました
But Jehovah doesn’t say,
しかしエホバは ネブカドネザルが
‘Nebuchadnezzar has destroyed
the city and its temple.’
神殿を滅ぼしたことについて
言っていたのではありません
He says:
“The people of a leader who is coming.”
「やがて来る指導者」が
滅ぼす となっています
The Roman general Titus in 70 C.E.
西暦70年にローマのティツス将軍が
「都市と聖なる場所を滅ぼ［す］」
ことについて言っていたのです
“will destroy the city and the holy place.”
In order for that prophecy to be fulfilled,
この預言が実現するには
エルサレムと神殿が再建され
Jerusalem and the temple
would have to be rebuilt
その後もう一度破壊される
ことが必要でした
and then destroyed a second time.
非常に具体的な情報や知識を
得ることができます
Now, that is quite a level of knowledge
—quite a level of information.
でも なぜこういうことに
なるのでしょうか
But what would make this necessary?
ユダヤ人が約束の地に戻り
Why, when the Jews
came back to the Promised Land
真の崇拝を回復しようとしたのに
and they were intent
on restoring true worship,
最終的にうまくいかなかったのは
なぜでしょうか
why would this fail?
エルサレムと神殿がもう一度
破壊されたのはなぜですか
And why would Jerusalem and the temple
be destroyed a second time?
Part of it is due to what we find
in the first part of verse 26:
今読んだ26節の前半に
ヒントがあります
「メシアは除かれます」とあります
“Messiah will be cut off.”
So Jehovah foretold, foresaw,
ですからエホバは メシアが来る時
ユダヤ人がメシアを退けることを見通し
予告していました
that when the Messiah came,
the Jews would reject him.
He would be cut off.
「メシアは除かれます」
And because of that, partly because of that,
ユダヤ人がメシアを殺したことも
理由になって
Jerusalem and the temple would be destroyed,
エルサレムと神殿が破壊されました
as it happens, in 70 C.E.
西暦70年のことです
Now, wait a minute, wait a minute.
でもちょっと待ってください
考えてみてください
Let’s think about that a minute.
The Messiah comes first
and Jerusalem and the temple
まずメシアが来て
その後西暦70年に
are destroyed after that in 70 C.E.
エルサレムと神殿が破壊されました
What does that mean?
どういうことですか
It means that the Messiah
comes before 70 C.E.
メシアは西暦70年よりも前に
来たということです
ユダヤ人の皆さんに
So we might ask our Jewish friends,
今でもメシアを待っているのは
なぜですかと聞きたいです
why are you still waiting for the Messiah?
70 C.E. has come and gone.
西暦70年はもう過ぎ去りました
Well, the Messiah came,
and he too proved to be a true prophet.
メシアは地に来て 自分が真の
預言者であることを実証しました
And a remarkable prophecy of Jesus
is found in the Sermon on the Mount.
イエスは山上の垂訓の中で
際立った預言をしました
Let’s have a look at it and consider
the implications of this prophecy.
その預言からどんなことが
分かるでしょうか
This is Matthew chapter 7,
マタイ 7章です
and we’ll read verses 22 and 23,
22, 23節を読みます
an amazing prophecy.
驚くべき預言です
Now, imagine: At this point, Jesus’ teachings
当時 イエスの教えは
イスラエル以外の所では
広まっていませんでした
have not spread beyond Israel.
But notice verses 22 and 23:
22, 23節です
“Many will say to me on that day:
「その日には 多くの人が
私に向かって『主よ 主よ
“‘Lord, Lord,
did we not prophesy in your name,
私たちはあなたの名
によって預言し⋯⋯
邪悪な天使たちを追い出し⋯⋯
“‘and expel demons in your name,
多くの強力な行いをしなかった
でしょうか』と言います
“and perform many powerful works
in your name?’
“And then I will declare to them:
‘I never knew you!
その時 私ははっきり言います
『あなたたちのことは全く知りません
Get away from me,
you workers of lawlessness!’”
不法なことをする人たち
離れ去りなさい！』」
Now, isn’t that amazing?
驚くべき預言です
If Jesus had simply predicted
イエスの教えが世界中に広まる
という預言であれば
that his teachings would spread
throughout the earth,
「大した預言ではない」と
思うかもしれません
you might say, “Well, there’s
nothing remarkable about that.”
But Jesus is saying something different.
でもイエスは そのようなことではなく
Jesus is foretelling
大規模な背教が生じることを
予告しました
a great apostasy from his teachings.
Jesus is foretelling the birth of Christendom
キリスト教世界の誕生を
予告していました
300 years before the event.
300年も前にです
So Jesus foresees that many
イエスは 多くの人が
真理から離れることを予告していました
are going to turn away from the truth.
And by the end of the first century,
1世紀の終わりまでには
that apostasy was already at work, wasn’t it?
背教がすでに生じていました
There were sects
ニコラオ派など さまざまな
分派が存在していました
—the sect of Nicolaus,
for example, and other sects.
And now they’re on the cusp
of the great darkness,
2世紀になると
背教はさらに進み
the great apostasy, that’s going to set in
from the second century on.
闇が深まっていきました
And with this in mind, what does Jehovah do?
では エホバの預言について
考えてみましょう
He makes an amazing statement
驚くような預言です
—Revelation 14—
啓示 14章です
「14万4000人」が「子羊と共に」
‘144,00 will be on Mount Zion with the Lamb.’
「シオンの山に立［つ］」とあります
There were nowhere near 144,000
in the truth in the first century.
1世紀当時 そんなに多くの
クリスチャンはいませんでした
And here Jehovah is saying
there are going to be 144,000 in heaven
でもエホバは 天で子羊と共に立つ人が
14万4000人になると述べています
with the Lamb at the end.
それだけではありません
But not only that, he goes further.
「誰も数え切れない大群衆」
についても述べています
There’s going to be
a ‘great crowd that no man can number.’
本当に実現するのでしょうか
How could that ever come true?
Ours is the God of true prophecy.
エホバは真の預言の神です
Well, that’s prophecy.
将来を見通すことができます
What about the second point?
2つ目の点です 預言の実現を
妨げることは誰にもできません
And that is that no one
can prevent prophecy from being fulfilled.
The Devil would love
to prevent that from taking place.
悪魔は妨げたいと思っています
啓示 14章について考えましょう
Think about Revelation 14.
悪魔は天に行く人の数が
14万4000人より
If the Devil could make the number
one short of 144,000,
1人でも少なければ
大喜びするでしょう
he’d be happy because he would show
エホバの預言が不正確だった
ということになるからです
that Jehovah was inaccurate
in what he foretold.
And so that’s one
of the reasons why the Devil
女の子孫のうちの残っている人たちと
戦ってきたのは
has made war on the remnant
of the seed of the woman,
そのためでもあります
if at all possible, to prevent that number
何とか14万4000人に
ならないようにしようとしています
of 144,000 from coming to pass.
もちろん その企ては成功しません
But, of course, he’s going to fail.
And what about the prophecy in the Bible
イギリスとアメリカが
世界の強国になるという
聖書の預言はどうでしょうか
that America and Britain
would become a dual world power?
フランスが阻止すれば
Now, Britain wouldn’t become a world power
イギリスは世界の強国に
ならなかったかもしれません
at all if France
had anything to say about it.
France and Britain were sworn enemies.
フランスとイギリスは敵対していました
And for many, many, years,
非常に長い間 フランスは
イギリスよりも
France was much richer
and much more powerful
はるかに豊かで強い国でした
than Britain was.
And finally,
at the Battle of Waterloo in 1815,
ところが 1815年の
ワーテルローの戦いで
France had one last chance
イギリスがフランスに勝利を収め
to prevent Britain
from becoming a world power.
世界の強国にのし上がりました
And France should have won that battle.
当初 イギリスには
勝ち目がなさそうでした
Everything was stacked against the British.
不利な要素ばかりでした
But there was a driving rain,
ところが 戦いの前夜に
大雨が降ったことや
a fatal miscalculation
on the part of Napoleon,
ナポレオンが大きな失敗を
したことなどが原因で
and a few other factors
that foiled their attempt.
フランスは敗れました
そのようにしてイギリスは
世界の強国になりました
And Britain did become a world power.
And at the end of the 19th century,
本当に興味深い進展です
it’s quite true that the sun
never set on the British Empire.
19世紀の終わりには
大英帝国は日の沈まない国となりました
But now, America and Britain
were supposed to become a dual world power,
では イギリスとアメリカはどのように
同盟関係を結んだのでしょうか
and Britain wasn’t the least bit interested
in sharing its power with America.
イギリスは当初 アメリカと
手を組むつもりはありませんでした
It tried to prevent America
from separating as a colony.
イギリスはアメリカの独立を
阻止しようとしました
There was a long war,
長い戦争の間 2国間の攻防が続き
and there were mistakes made on both sides.
But finally, America gained
its independence from Britain.
ついにアメリカが
イギリスから独立しました
Well, what do we find?
その後どうなりましたか
Some years after that,
Britain is sharing its power with America.
イギリスがアメリカと手を組み
あたかも1つの強国のように
なったのです
They are a dual world power.
Fighters against God will never prevail.
エホバの預言は必ず実現します
We serve “the God of true prophecy.”
エホバは真の預言の神です
And “what he foretells comes to be.”
私たちはその証人です
As we’ve discussed,
これまで考えた通り
each detail of the prophecy
recorded at Daniel chapter 11
ダニエル 11章の預言は
細かな点に至るまで実現してきました
has come true so far.
We must have confidence
私たちは 預言の残りの部分も
必ず実現する という
that the remaining events
described in that prophecy
確信を持たなければなりません
will also come true.
We are living in the last days
of the time of the end.
この終わりの時は
もうすぐ終わりを迎えます
Soon, the nations will fulfill the prophecy
間もなく テサロニケ第一 5:3の
次の預言が実現します
at 1 Thessalonians 5:3:
“Whenever it is that they are saying,
「人々は 『平和だ 安全だ！』と
言っている時に
“‘Peace and security!’
“then sudden destruction
is to be instantly on them,
突然滅ぼされることになります
“just like birth pains on a pregnant woman,
妊婦に起こる陣痛と同じように突然で
彼らは決して逃れられません」
and they will by no means escape.”
Then “sudden destruction”
その時 サタンの体制全てが
「突然滅ぼされ」ます
comes upon all parts of Satan’s system.
As you can see on the screen,
画面をご覧ください
Daniel 12:1 says:
ダニエル 12:1にはこうあります
“During that time Michael will stand up,
「その時 あなたの民のために
立っている
“the great prince who is standing
in behalf of your people.
偉大な長ミカエルが行動を起こします
“And there will occur a time of distress
such as has not occurred
そして 国が始まってからその時まで
生じたことがない苦難の時が来ます
“since there came to be a nation
until that time.
“And during that time
your people will escape,
その時 あなたの民
書に記されている人は皆 逃れます」
everyone who is found written down
in the book.”
That leads us into our third point:
では 3つ目の点を考えましょう
How should knowing the information
今日ご一緒に考えた事柄は 私たちの
生き方にどんな影響を与えますか
that we have just discussed
affect the decisions that we make?
Well, what we have reviewed
is not just interesting history;
今回振り返ったのは 単なる
興味深い歴史ではありません
it’s a dramatic prelude
間もなく地上で起こる
素晴らしい事柄の前触れです
to what will soon happen here on earth.
Jehovah has given his people this knowledge
エホバがこうしたことを知らせている
のは 私たちが行動するためです
so that we can act on it.
It should influence the choices we make.
賢い決定をする必要があります
次のビデオをご覧ください
In the following dramatization,
notice how one young brother makes decisions
ある若い兄弟は
ダニエルの預言についてよく考えて
based on his understanding
of Daniel’s prophecy.
どんな決定をするでしょうか
That was my best friend, Lucas,
小さい頃から仲良しのルーカス
そしてこれが僕 オスカー
when we were kids.
And that was me, Oscar.
大きくなったらやりたいことは決まってた
We knew exactly what we wanted to do
when we grew up:
開拓奉仕！
ベテル奉仕！
Pioneer!
Go to Bethel!
Build Kingdom Halls!
王国会館の建設！
We kept those goals.
ずっと頑張ってきて
And when graduation came,
卒業する時までには準備万端だった
we were ready.
清掃の仕事を始めた
Our little business needed
just a few more accounts.
あと何人かお客さんがいれば
十分やっていけるし
Then we’d have enough for us
and to help our families.
家族も助けられる
ついに来た！
奉仕年度の初日
Finally!
Day one of the service year
—and two new pioneers!
2人とも開拓者になった！
でもこの区域で⋯⋯
Where we live, . . .
もうかけてこないでください
Please don’t call me ever again!
⋯⋯聖書に興味がある人を
見つけるのは難しい
. . . finding spiritual interest is tough.
間に合ってます
We already have cleaners.
Thanks.
お客さんを見つけるのも
思ったより大変だった
And finding enough work
was harder than we thought.
何カ月かたった
A few months in,
I was sure
頑張って続けていれば
エホバが助けてくれると信じていた
Jehovah would help
if we just stuck it out.
Sorry, Oscar.
Can’t make it today.
ごめん オスカー今日は行けない
ちょっと用事ができた ルーカス
Something came up.
Lucas.
What came up
was an opportunity for more money,
用事というのは
もっといい仕事の話だった
but at what cost?
どういうつもりなんだ
Are you quitting, or what?
やめるつもりなの？
No, I’m not quitting.
いや やめないよ
Pioneering or our business?
開拓を？仕事を？
どっちもだよ
でも大変なのは分かるだろ？
Neither, but you know the struggle here.
1年でやめちゃう人が多いよね
せいぜい2年とか
Most brothers can afford
to pioneer for a year, two tops.
仕事はフルタイムでやるって
決めたわけじゃない
Look, it’s not full-time while I’m training.
It’s a backup plan.
万一のためだよ
ルーカス 開拓やめたんだ
So Lucas stopped pioneering?
正解かもね
Maybe he’s right.
現実を見てる
He’s just being practical.
本当に難しかったら
開拓やめてもいいんだよね？
I mean, is it wrong to quit
if you think it’s not working?
お母さんも同じことで悩んだことがある
I struggled with the same question
when I pioneered.
どう決定するにしても
Whatever you decide,
if you can tell Jehovah your reason
エホバに理由をきちんと説明できるなら
with a clean conscience,
あなたにとって良い決定なんだと思う
then it’s the right decision for you.
こんなに大変なのに なんで
頑張らなきゃいけないんだろう
Why would I keep going
when it’s so difficult?
「これらのものは全て
このように溶解するのですから
“Since all these things
are to be dissolved in this way,
自分がどんな人に
なるべきかを考えてください
“consider what sort of people
you ought to be
in holy acts of conduct
and deeds of godly devotion.”
聖なる振る舞いをし
神への専心を行動に表し」
今は本当に「終わりの時代」だ
It really is “the last days,”
and people need “the good news.”
人々は「良い知らせ」を必要としている
And they’ll only hear it
僕たちが「神への専心を
行動で表」さないと
if we keep up our “deeds of godly devotion”
人々は良い知らせを聞くことはできない
as best we can.
I prayed to endure and only stop pioneering
エホバに祈った
できるところまで最大限頑張って
開拓奉仕を続けます
if my circumstances left no other choice.
どうか 祝福してください
And I prayed to see the blessings.
少したって気付いた
And after a while,
エホバの力に頼って
ちょっと頑張るだけで
I learned that a little perseverance,
with Jehovah’s spirit, can be contagious.
他の人の励みになれる
So, what do you want to do
when you grow up?
ねえ 大きくなったら
どうしたいんだっけ？
開拓者
Pioneer.
And go to Bethel?
で ベテル？
Yep!
そう その後 王国会館の建設だろ？
And then maybe build Kingdom Halls.
You in?
Yeah.
うん
この兄弟は どんな生き方を
したらよいか真剣に考えました
That young brother was trying to figure out
what to do with his life.
聖書の預言をよく学び
考え方を調整したので
He made a good decision
because he allowed Bible prophecy
良い決定ができました
to influence his thinking.
We know that teens everywhere
10代の皆さんはいろんな
問題にぶつかっています
face many challenges, and we feel for you.
本当に大変だと思います
Of course, I was once a teenager,
今の若い皆さんは 私が10代の頃には
but I can’t even imagine
some of the situations
経験しなかったような問題と
闘っていることでしょう
that you find yourselves in.
But the Governing Body loves you,
統治体は皆さんを愛し
助けたいと思っています
and we want to help.
それで 新しいビデオシリーズを
始めることにしました
So I’m very happy to announce a new series
—“My Teen Life.”
「10代の頃の私」です
You’ll hear from Witnesses
兄弟姉妹が10代の頃
どんな問題にぶつかり
who share the challenges
they faced in their teens
エホバの助けでどのように
乗り越えたかを話してくれます
and how they overcame them
with Jehovah’s help.
The interviews are candid;
実際に経験したことについて
本音で語っています
the issues are real.
Here’s the first episode.
第1回をお楽しみください
10代の時は 親と話したって
無駄だと思ってました
Well, when I was a teenager,
I didn’t see any benefit
in talking to my parents
because they
liked different things than I liked.
親とは好きなこととかも違うし
話したって意味ないって感じでした
So I thought, ‘Well, what’s the point?’
And I also wanted to be an adult.
それに もう子供じゃないんだから
自分で何でもできるって思ってました
I wanted to feel like an adult
and be treated like an adult.
I remember when my mom
used to pick me up from school.
学校に迎えに来た母は
車の中でいろいろ尋ねてきました
She wanted to show personal interest in me,
so she’d ask me:
“Oh, how are your friends doing?
「みんなと仲良くやってる？
変わったことなかった？
宿題はたくさんあるの？」
“How was school today?
Do you have a lot of homework?”
But I just thought that she was being nosy.
「ほっといてよ」って感じでした
I always had my earphones on.
それでいつもヘッドホンをしてました
And whenever my parents
were trying to talk to me,
親から話し掛けられると すぐに
ヘッドホンを付けて無視してました
that was my chance
to just pop them in and ignore them.
親が育った環境は私とは違います
The way my parents grew up wasn’t
the same way that I grew up.
国も違いますし 言語も違います
They grew up in a different country;
they spoke a different language;
they grew up in a different time.
時代も違います
自分とは母語が違う人と話していると
When you’re talking to somebody
who doesn’t speak your language natively,
気持ちがうまく伝わらなくて
もどかしく感じることがあります
oftentimes you won’t be able
to explain things from your heart.
And so I had that challenge.
私もそうでした 親に本音で
話すことはできませんでした
I wasn’t able to talk directly
to my parents heart to heart.
いつもイライラしていました
And so there was always this frustration
本当の気持ちがなかなか
伝わらなかったからです
in trying to really convey how I felt.
親に分かってもらうのは
無理だ と思っていました
And I felt like I
wasn’t really getting through to my parents.
初めて開拓者学校に行った時
エホバについて深く学びました
When I went to my first pioneer school,
I learned a lot about Jehovah’s qualities.
And one of them was
how he was a very approachable Person.
例えば エホバは
とても近づきやすい方です
And I thought to myself,
‘Am I an approachable person?’
自分はどうだろう と考えました
近づきやすいだろうか
And I thought about how
I acted in the ministry
伝道や集会の時や家での
自分はどうだろう と考えました
and then at the meetings and then at home.
And I realized that at home
I had a lot of things I needed to fix.
直さなければいけないところが
たくさんありました
2つの世界に
住んでいるような感じでした
I felt like it was two different worlds
I was living in.
One was when I was at school with my peers;
1つは学校で 友達には
分かってもらえると感じました
I felt like I was understood.
でも家では 殻に閉じこもっていました
And at home,
I kind of just withdrew to myself.
I wouldn’t try to communicate with them
because it didn’t seem worth the effort.
親と話そうとは思いませんでした
無駄だと思ったからです
I tried to figure out problems in my own way.
自分で何とかしようとしました
でもうまくいきませんでした
It was kind of trial and error.
I developed a lot of bad habits
いろんな問題を抱えるようになって
今も努力中です
that today I’m still trying to overcome.
親にもっと相談していればよかったです
If I’d been able
to communicate with them more,
親とのつながりを
大切にして助けてもらい
if I’d been able to connect
with them and ask for their help
and get their support
and have them on my team,
一緒に取り組んでいたら
いろんな問題を避けられたと思います
things would have gone a lot better.
And I really wish I had.
本当にそう思います
イエスは完全で完璧な
判断力を持っていましたが
Jesus, who was a perfect human being
and who had perfect judgment,
didn’t make decisions on his own.
自分だけで決定しようとはしませんでした
He always looked to his Father for guidance.
いつもお父さんに頼りました
And that got me thinking,
それでこう思いました
「イエスがそうしたんだから
‘Well, if Jesus did that,
‘there has to be something good
私もそうしなくちゃいけない」
in it for me too.’
What really helped me was Colossians 4:6.
コロサイ 4:6が助けになりました
I knew I needed to speak
more graciously in the family.
親に穏やかに話す
必要がある と思いました
And I realized
that I was speaking very defensively
親と話す時いつも壁を作っていたので
もっと近づきやすく
ならなくちゃ と思いました
and that I needed
to be more approachable to my parents.
When I first tried to talk with them,
of course,
それで努力してみたんですが
最初はぎこちない感じでした
it was awkward and I didn’t want to talk
about anything personal
慣れていなかったので なかなか
本当の気持ちを言えませんでした
because I wasn’t used to it.
それで逆に 親に
質問してみようと思いました
So I thought I could maybe
ask them about themselves
—ask them how their day was
or what they liked from the meetings.
「どんな一日だった？」とか
「集会で何が良かった？」とかです
So I just tried to show more interest in them
自分だけでなく親のことも
考えるようにしたんです
instead of focusing on myself.
そうしたら親といろいろ
話せるようになって
And I think that’s what got
the conversations going
自分の気持ちも言いやすくなりました
and got me comfortable
to really talk with them.
I was so focused on how my parents
weren’t understanding me
親は自分のことを分かってくれない
とずっと思っていました
that I wasn’t really trying
to understand them.
でも私の方が親を理解しようと
していませんでした
When I thought about my parents,
それで 親についていろいろと
考えてみました
I thought about how much work
it takes to be a parent.
親は本当に大変だと思います
From when I was a baby, for many years,
私が赤ちゃんの頃からずっと
昼も夜も休みなく世話してくれました
they were working day and night
to try to care for me.
They never demanded a thank you
or anything from me.
でも親から「感謝しなさい」
などと言われたことはありません
They were really self-sacrificing.
無私の愛を示してくれました
And I imagined:
‘If I had to work that much for somebody,
それでこう考えました 「もし自分が
それほどのことを誰かにしてあげたのに
‘how would I feel if they
didn’t really say thank you?
『ありがとう』って言って
もらえなかったらどう感じるだろう
‘Or how would I feel
一生懸命尽くしたのに 友達と
見てくれなかったらどう思うだろう」
‘if this person whom I worked so hard for
didn’t really view me as their friend?’
Later on, as I got older and started
だんだんと親との会話が
うまくいくようになりました
that communication going with my parents,
親の言うことをちゃんと聞いて
アドバイスにも従って
I realized that taking their advice
and really listening to their opinions
自分が何をしたいとか
どこに行きたいとかいうことを
and always letting them know
what I’m going to do
and where I’m going to go
親にきちんと伝えておくのが
大切なんだっていうことが分かりました
was a mature thing to do.
Our heart oftentimes
心の赴くままに車を運転すると
takes the driver’s seat, and it directs us
自分では正しい方向に
向かっていると思っていても
to where it thinks it should go.
And oftentimes it goes
in the wrong direction,
間違った方向に
進んでしまうことがあります
and we sometimes get hurt.
問題に陥るかもしれません
Then we look back and say,
“I wish I hadn’t done that.”
「あんなことしなければ
よかった」と思います
And our parents have been there.
親も若い頃同じような
経験をしているので
What they’re trying to do
for us now is to tell us,
「心の赴くままに運転しないように」って
言ってくれるんです
“Don’t let your heart
take the driver’s seat.”
If I could talk to my teenage self,
10代の自分にアドバイス
できるとしたら
I would tell myself to see
my mom and dad more like coaches,
「親はコーチみたいなもん
なんだよ」って言いたいです
以前は親からいつも批判されたり
because I used to think
they were always trying to criticize me
欠点を指摘されたりしている
と感じていたからです
and point out my faults.
But, really, they’re just trying to help me,
でも本当は 私を助けたい
and they want me to have a happy life.
幸せになってほしい
と思ってくれていたんです
I really wish I knew that as a teenager.
10代の頃に気付けたら
よかったんですけど
But I’m glad I learned that now.
でも今分かってよかったです
We hope that you’ll enjoy and benefit
今後の「10代の頃の私」シリーズも
楽しみにしていてください
from future episodes of “My Teen Life.”
This new series is another way
統治体がこの新しい
シリーズを準備したのは
the Governing Body prepares Jehovah’s people
エホバに仕える人たちが
今の問題に対処し
to cope with today’s challenges
将来に備えられるようにするためです
and to be ready for what’s coming.
Bible prophecy shows that in the near future,
聖書の預言によれば 間もなく
the nations will turn
on all false religions and wipe them out.
諸国家は間違った宗教を
全て除き去ります
Then, they will launch
a final attack on God’s people.
その後 神の民に最終的な
攻撃を仕掛けます
And what a mistake that will be!
何と愚かなことでしょう
As discussed in the Pure Worship{
「清い崇拝」の本にある通り
Jehovah will respond to that attack
エホバは諸国家に怒りを表し
by unleashing his rage on the nations.
攻撃します
After the dust of Armageddon settles,
ハルマゲドンが終わった後
those with the earthly hope can look forward
地上で生きる希望を持つ人たちは
to a thousand years
of genuine peace and security,
1000年間 神の王国の統治の下
真の平和と安全を楽しむことができます
working under the rule of God’s Kingdom.
Before that time comes,
それまでの間
we will continue to face
trials and opposition,
私たちは試練や反対に遭いますが
耐え忍ぶことができます
but we can endure.
We have many modern-day examples
私たちの良い手本になっている人は
that we can imitate right now.
今も大勢います
Those examples can help all of us
そうした手本に倣うことで
十分な備えをし しっかり立ち
to be prepared, to stand firm,
仲間と一致してエホバに
仕えていくことができます
and to remain fully united in the faith.
This month’s original song
「私たちは共に立つ」という
entitled “One United People”
今月のオリジナルソングは
encourages us to do just that.
そうする助けになることでしょう
雲行きが悪い 予期した通り
We watch the storm clouds gather.
We’ve seen the signs before.
迫害の波が打ち付けてきた
The wind of persecution
Is no stranger to our door.
恐れなくていい 神が助ける
We will face each test with courage,
With Jehovah standing near.
敵の攻撃に勝利などない
And ‘no weapon formed against us’
Will give any cause for fear.
We are
one united people,
共に立とう さあ 心合わせて
Though we come
from ev’ry land.
神はすぐそばにいて 力与える
We are
standing firm together,
For Jehovah
makes us stand,
力与える
For Jehovah
makes us stand.
心が安らぐ 嵐の時も
We wait with calm assurance
For Jehovah, the Most High—
至高者の愛が共にあるから
The God of our salvation
Whose love will never die.
聖なる力で勇気みなぎる
He will never leave his people,
And his spirit makes us strong.
敵の脅しにも ひるみはしない
No, our enemies won’t break us.
To Jehovah we belong!
共に立とう さあ 心合わせて
We are
one united people,
Though we come
from ev’ry land.
神はすぐそばにいて 力与える
We are
standing firm together,
For Jehovah
makes us stand.
瞳閉じて 思い馳せれば
We stand firm together;
Unafraid we face the crowd.
And these hearts that beat within us
We have given to our God.
揺るがない友が海の向こうにも
共に立とう さあ 心合わせて
We are
one united people,
Though we come
from ev’ry land.
神はすぐそばにいて 力与える
We are
standing firm together,
For Jehovah
makes us stand,
神よ 力を
For Jehovah
makes us stand.
The stirring theme of this year’s convention
今年の地区大会のテーマは何でしょうか
is “Powerful By Faith!”
「信仰によって強くなる」です
We will learn what faith is,
信仰とは何ですか
why it is essential,
信仰が大切なのはなぜですか
and how we can acquire it.
どうすれば信仰を持てますか
Here is a preview.
紹介ビデオをご覧ください
It can be hard to put faith
in something you cannot see.
見えないものを信じるのは
簡単ではありません
But real faith is not blind.
ただ信じるのが
信仰というわけではありません
本当の信仰は 事実 実在するもの
Real faith is based on facts,
on realities,
確かな教えに基づいています
on truth.
勇気と力を与えてくれます
It gives us courage and strength,
つらい時も負けないで済みます
and it helps us to endure.
大変な時も落ち着かせてくれます
When life gets hard, it provides peace.
It reminds us of our purpose,
神の願いを意識させてくれます
and it brings us real joy.
深い喜びを与えてくれます
Learn how to build and strengthen your faith
どうすれば強い信仰を持てますか
at the 2021 “Powerful by Faith!”
Convention of Jehovah’s Witnesses.
エホバの証人の2021年
「信仰によって強くなる」
大会にご出席ください
Now it’s time for our video postcard,
which comes to us
ではこれからビデオレターを
楽しみましょう
今回はベラルーシの兄弟姉妹から
寄せられています
from our brothers and sisters in Belarus.
Belarus is an Eastern European nation
that borders Russia.
ベラルーシはロシアと国境を接する
東ヨーロッパの国です
It’s known as
「青い目の国」と呼ばれています
the “blue-eyed” country
because it is dotted
1万以上の湖があるからです
with more than 10,000 lakes.
Some of Europe’s
most ancient trees, as well as
ヨーロッパ最古の原生林もあります
また ヨーロッパ最大の哺乳類
its largest mammal
—the European bison—
ヨーロッパバイソンもいます
can be found here.
Castles, some dating
16世紀に建てられた城もあり
from the 16th century, are popular sites.
人気の観光スポットになっています
This is Nesvizh Castle.
これはネスビシ城です
If you look up at the ceiling of its chapel,
you’ll see Jehovah’s name
礼拝堂の天井には エホバの名が
テトラグラマトンで記されています
in the form of the Tetragrammaton.
When Belarus was part of the Soviet Union,
ベラルーシがソビエト連邦の
一部だった頃
Jehovah’s Witnesses
faced strong government opposition.
エホバの証人は政府からの
強い弾圧を受けました
遠くシベリアに追放された
兄弟たちもいます
Some of our brothers
were exiled to far-away Siberia.
Today, more than 6,000 publishers
現在ベラルーシでは
84の会衆にいる
6000人以上の伝道者が
in 84 congregations
boldly declare the good news
良い知らせを大胆に伝えています
in Belarus.
兄弟姉妹は熱意にあふれています
There is a zealous pioneer spirit here.
Twenty percent of the publishers
伝道者の20パーセント以上が
全時間奉仕をしています
are in full-time service.
これは ブレストで良い知らせを
伝えている兄弟姉妹です
This is how our brothers share the good news
in the city of Brest.
They enjoy many aspects
さまざまな方法で伝道を楽しんでいます
of public witnessing.
Here are our brothers and sisters
in the city of Kobryn.
これは コブリンで奉仕している
兄弟姉妹です
Their territory includes
both urban and rural areas.
都会の区域もあれば
田舎の区域もあります
The 78 publishers here conduct an average
78人の伝道者が
毎月平均74件の
聖書レッスンを行っています
of 74 Bible studies each month.
ベラルーシの兄弟姉妹が温かい
愛とあいさつを送っています
Our brothers and sisters in Belarus
send you their warm love and greetings.
ファン･セルム兄弟 ご一緒に
Herman, it’s been a pleasure
reviewing this exciting material
「北の王」について考えることが
できてうれしかったです
about the “king of the north” with you.
ありがとうございます
Thank you, Ken.
今日学んだ内容は非常に大切です
This information is so important.
It helps all of us
私たち全てが 確信を持って
将来に備える助けになります
to face the future with confidence.
Before we say goodbye,
we have a treat for you.
お別れする前に
お見せしたいものがあります
Here’s a preview of the video drama
from this year’s convention.
今年の地区大会で上映される
ドラマの予告編です
どうぞお楽しみください
Please enjoy.
You will receive training
おまえは 偉大な王ネブカドネザルの
王宮で訓練を受ける
in the house of the great King Nebuchadnezzar.
待ってください
Wait!
ダニエル！
Daniel!
勇気を出すんだ
Be strong, my son.
国も法律も違うんだ
This is a new land with new laws.
次は宗教かな？
Soon they’ll want us to worship their gods.
エホバはイスラエルにいる
Jehovah is in Israel.
ここはバビロンだ
We’re in Babylon now.
僕たちどうなるんだろう？
What’s going to happen to us?
王が夢を見た
でもどんな夢だったか誰も話せない
He had a dream,
and no one can tell him what it is.
賢人たちが王の逆鱗に触れて
明朝処刑されます
Everyone is to be executed by dawn.
We have until morning.
朝までに何とかしないと
To do what?
何を？
It’s Jerusalem.
エルサレムが・・・
エホバの家が焼け落ちた
They burned down Jehovah’s house!
エホバは生きておられる 望みはあるわ
As long as Jehovah exists,
we have hope.
私の神エホバなら解き明かせます
Interpretations belong to my God, Jehovah.
王が見た夢と その意味を
He knows your dream and what it means.
おまえの神の言葉を聞かせろ！
Where is your God?
処刑しろ！
Kill them!
O Jehovah,
エホバ ここに来たのは
死ぬためではないはずです
surely you didn’t bring us here to die.
どうか 力をお示しください
Please, vindicate yourself.
As we’ve discussed in our program,
今月のプログラムで学んだように
Daniel played an important role
as Jehovah’s prophet.
エホバの預言者ダニエルは
大切な役割を果たしました
And as we’ll see in our video drama,
大会のドラマでは
ダニエルの生き方から
there’s much we can learn
from his life and example.
さらに多くのことを学ぶことができます
最後にもう1つプレゼントがあります
And now, before we sign off,
we have a special musical gift video
今月のプログラムの
テーマに密接に関連した
that closely relates
to our monthly program theme.
特別なミュージックビデオを
お届けします
You will be encouraged and inspired.
力と勇気が湧いてくるでしょう
これからもロシアの兄弟姉妹
のために祈ってください
Please keep our brothers
in Russia in your prayers.
Learn from their example
of faith and courage.
兄弟姉妹の信仰と勇気に倣いましょう
See these events for what they are
今起きている出来事は聖書の預言が
実現していることの証拠です
—the fulfillment of Bible prophecy.
Let this knowledge
move you to make wise decisions.
ですから これからも正しい
決定を下すようにしましょう
Stay faithful, and stay busy
終わりが近い今 信仰を保ち
as the end of this system draws close.
熱心に奉仕し続けましょう
From the World Headquarters
of Jehovah’s Witnesses,
エホバの証人の世界本部から
this is JW Broadcasting.
JW Broadcastingでした